# Joshua Benjamin

256 E. Jackson St. New Holland, PA, 17557

**PHONE**: (717) 538-0866 **E-Mail**: jbenj@sas.upenn.edu \*\*\*\* jdb354@drexel.edu

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I am an English Language Instructor with expertise in reading, writing, listening, and speaking instruction, with a successful track record of strong student reviews year after year, in addition to positive in-class observations from various colleagues.

I possess a varied professional career, beginning with secondary instruction, including a start-up charter school, continuing to higher education instruction.

# **Present Professional Continuing Educational Endeavor**

Most recently, I have begun studying in a full-stack (i.e., front-end and back-end instruction) computer coding "bootcamp" through the University of Pennsylvania and Trilogy Educational Services. My graduation date from this program is in early August, 2020. I plan to pursue a career in this field, specifically as either a front- or back-end developer, ideally working for a company that is teamwork/collaboration-oriented.

#### **HIGHLIGHTS**

**Instruction**: Individually manage logistics of numerous courses, including, but not limited to, attendance, maintenance of grades, and implementation of various requisite assignments; well-versed in providing assessment to students, both formatively and sumatively; identify students' deficiencies in their language proficiencies and work to create unique plans to overcome them.

**Student Relations:** Provide sensitive cultural information to students from disparate international locations in order to lessen the effects of culture shock; play the role of liason and mediator when cultural and linguistic misunderstandings arise; foster an environment that is student-centered and hinges on tolerance towards, appreciation for, and acceptance of diverse backgrounds and sensitivities.

**Professional Development:** Attend formal meetings, presentations, and conferences designed to increase the effectiveness of educators in widely varying aspects; engage in informal, self-driven research and implementation of current best practices in the field.

**Team Building:** Interact with colleagues both formally and informally to give and receive feedback regarding the full spectrum of in-class practices that regularly arise.

**Organizational Development:** Constantly hone skills pertaining to the proper maintenance of class records and lesson plans, as well as supplemental resources that are distributed or otherwise shared to aid students' progress.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE HIGHLIGHTS

### University of Pennsylvania, English Language Program- Philadelphia, PA

Consistently ranked in the top 10 of American universities, the University of Pennsylvania boasts over 20,000 students, 25% of whom hail from outside of the United States.

#### **Guest Lecturer –** January 2013-present

Plan, manage, and teach a variety of core Reading/Writing and Listening/Speaking courses, as well
as a wide variety of elective courses, receiving well above average student reviews in almost all
cases.

- Provide continual formative and summative feedback to students.
- Attend optional professional development meetings.
- Regularly check in with Peer Coaches, scheduling observation times and opportunities for feedback and professional growth.

# Drexel University — Philadelphia, PA

❖ A well-known research university, Drexel has more than 25,000 students, roughly 13% of whom are international.

# Adjunct English Professor - January 2010-present

- Plan, teach, and manage English 101 (Rhetoric in Writing), 102 (Evidence-Based Research in Writing), and 103 (Dystopian Literature in Composition) in the First-Year Writing Program.
- Provide rigorous student feedback in order to raise levels of proficiency in writing.
- Formerly taught a wide variety of courses in the English Language Center, including American Culture and Conversation, Listening and Speaking, and Vocabulary Development, among others.

## Millersville University— Millersville, PA

Just outside of Lancaster City, Millersville is a state university known for training highly qualified primary and secondary school educators.

## Adjunct English Professor- September 2016-January 2017

- Planned, taught, and managed Transformational Grammar course.
- Conducted lectures around Traditional, Structural, and Transformational schools of grammar.
- Prepared all class presenations.
- Conducted a one-on-one Winter session with a student who needed to retake the course.
- Facilitated group discussions on various course topics.
- Administered exams and provide feedback.

# Harrisburg Area Community College— Lancaster, PA

Provides mostly local, but widely diverse students with a starting point for their college careers.

#### English as an Additional Language Instructor- September 2012-June 2013

- Planned, taught, and managed a variety of English Language Learner courses that touched on all four language skills.
- Created an inclusive, empowering learning environment that treasured learners' unique backgrounds, especially their first languages.
- Sought to portray the acquisition of English as a tool for social mobility, dispelling notions of elitism.
- Conducted exploration/discovery-based lessons and projects focused on vocabulary, grammar, pronunciation, and writing.
- Demonstrated active listening and reading techniques to aid student comprehension.
- Provided focused feedback when students' pronunciation sufficiently impeded successful communication.

## La Academia Partnership Charter School— Lancaster, PA

Also known as LAPCS, La Academia services mostly at-risk middle and high school students.

## **ESL Teacher-** September 2009-June 2010

• Implemented a push-in educational model for a population that was 80% non-native English speakers.

## Living Word Academy (now Lancaster County Christian School) — Lancaster, PA

❖ This is a private, interdenominational school in Lancaster County known for its quality education.

# **Spainsh Teacher (High school)-** September 2003- January 2008

- Planned, taught, and managed all aspects of High School Spanish courses, all levels (1-5).
- Coordinated various trips as head chaperone and organizer to other cities and countries for educational and volunteering purposes.

# Instituto Centro America— Quetzaltenango, Guatemala

❖ ICA is a Spanish language school, also offering English courses to local Guatemalans.

# English as a Foreign Language Teacher- June-July 2005

- Volunteered as a tutor for Guatemalan EFL students.
- Helped lead trips and social and language activities to places all over the country.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of Pennsylvania/Trilogy Educational Services, present (2020)- currently pursuing certification as a full-stack computer developer.

West Chester University, 2010- West Chester, PA; earned a Master's of Arts in TESL (Teaching English as a Second Language); Cumulative GPA- 4.0/4.0

*Millersville University, 2003*- Millersville, PA; earned a double major Bachelor's of Arts in English Linguistics and ESL (English as a Second Language) with a Spanish minor; Cumulative GPA- 3.54/4.0

#### MISCELLANEOUS WORK EXPERIENCE

# Stoner Grille, Lancaster City, PA- June 2018-Present on an as-needed basis

Bartender

## Federal Taphouse, Lancaster City, PA— April 2016-September 2019

Private Events Bartender and Server

#### Olive Garden, Lancaster City, PA— September 2000-October 2015

Server, Bartender

# Barny's Restaurant, Lancaster, PA— Summer 2010

Server, Bartender

# Teen Haven, Lancaster City, PA 2001-2004

Youth Counselor

#### **ADDITIONAL SKILLS AND HOBBIES**

## **Systems Expertise**

Microsoft Office, Prezi, Canvas, Blackboard, iWebfolio, Turnitin

## **Developmental Computer Languages and Skills**

HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, API client-side server calls, Node.JS

Languages	
Languages Spanish (fluent), some French, and can introduce myself in numerous languages	
Hobbies	
Billiards, Poker, "Street" Art/Murals, Reading, Fitness	